"An enthusiastic graduate Student in Computer Science currently looking for **Full Time Opportunities** who has more than 4 years of industry experience in software design and development. A committed team player with excellent problem solving and communication skills, with proven success in various academic and job-related engagements.

EDUCATION

Master of Science, Computer Science, University of Texas at Dallas, United States GPA: 3.91/4.0 Aug 2016-present

- *Coursework:* Statistics for Data Science, Database Design, Machine Learning, Design and Analysis of Algorithms, Big Data, Artificial Intelligence, Software Testing Verification and Validation, Object Oriented Design.
- Graduate <u>scholarship recipient</u> at UTD Erik Jonsson School of Engineering (Obtained a score of 324 in GRE).

B-Tech., Computer Science, National Institute of Technology -Calicut, India GPA:7.21/10(First Class) Apr 2012

- *Coursework:* Data Structures and Algorithms, Database Management Systems, Advanced Data Structures, Principles of Programming Languages, Software Design, Web Programming.
- National Institute of Technology-Calicut is one of the <u>premier government Engineering institutes</u> in India.

SOFTWARE SKILLS

Proficient : C++, MySql, Oracle, Python, Java, OOD. **Intermediate :** Javascript, HTML5, CSS, Git, XML, JSON, UML.

Familiar: Hadoop, jQuery, Web Services, Service Oriented Architecture, Apache Spark, JUnit.

WORK EXPERIENCE

Senior Applications Engineer, Oracle India Private Limited, India

Jun 2015-Jul 2016

(C++, SQL, PeopleCode, JavaScript)

- <u>Single handedly</u> designed and implemented a new Japanese HR software called 'My Number' based on an agile based iterative development process, using application level encryption using symmetric technique, Object Oriented Programming, role based security and workflow self service.
- Customer base for the HR Japan product <u>increased</u> <u>threefold</u> in the fiscal following the release of the above application. Received an <u>Oracle Excellence Award</u> for the project.
- Proposed an award winning gamification enabled internal review system where employees could rate the system pages/functionalites within our product, propose changes to them, participate in quizzes etc to win various rewards.
- Mentored and trained new resources in the team, thus preparing them for their respective job roles.
- Delivered product bug fixes and implemented additional functionalities to customers based on their requirements with less than 1% defects.

Applications Engineer, Oracle India Private Limited, India

Jul 2012-May 2015

(C++,PeopleCode, Java, SQL)

- <u>Key member of the cross-functional team</u> that consolidated the Entity Relationship Diagrams (ERD) model which detailed the table loading sequence for all the components within HCM module which helped optimize system <u>by</u> more than 20%.
- Brought down the defect backlog of a customer by <u>80% in a span of 1 month</u> whereas the normal average was 15-20% for a team.
- One of the very few in the team of 20 members to have worked on all the modules handled by the team.
- Awarded above average <u>rating of 3+ (Exceeding Expectations</u>) at Oracle India for the year 2013 in just one year after starting my professional career.

PROJECT EXPERIENCE

In Memory File System May 2017

• Built an in-memory file system in <u>C++</u> that allowed all the basic operations like creating, deleting and moving of files and directories, reading and writing of files etc.

• It uniquely allowed users to specify the memory size limit for the system to prevent dynamic growth and provided an option to write the data from the file system to disk at periodic intervals.

Relational Database management system

May 2017

• Implemented a fully functional Relational Database management system in <u>Python</u> that could handle basic SQL queries such as selection, projection, join and aggregation efficiently using B+ trees.

Test Suite Prioritization Tool

Apr-May 2017

- Created a time-aware total/ additional test prioritization tool in <u>Java</u> using <u>ASM</u> <u>byte-code</u> manipulation framework based on the statement coverage metric.
- This tool generated the order of execution of the test cases and then scheduled them according to the total time allotted for Regression Testing.

Pump it Up- Data Mining the Water Table

Apr-May 2017

- Successfully predicted the operating condition of water pumps in Tanzanian villages as part of a competition held on drivendata.org in which we were ranked in the top 50.
- An ensemble of Linear Regression, Ada Boosting, Random Forests and Deep Learning Networks were used .

Tweet Classification

Mar-Apr 2017

• Implemented an algorithm in <u>Python</u> to cluster tweets on boston bombings to measure the sentiment analysis by utilizing the Jaccard Distance metric and K-means clustering algorithm.

Machine Learners for Classification- A comparative Study

Feb-Mar 2017

- Implemented machine learning techniques including ID3 decision tree with pruning and random selection (<u>C++</u>),
 Neural Net(C++), k- Nearest Neighbours, ensemble techniques, Multinomial Naive Bayes (<u>Python</u>).
- They were compared with each other by testing their effectiveness on real world raw data sets after data pre-processing/ feature engineering (<u>Python</u>).

Object Oriented Design for Payroll System

Sep-Nov 2016

- Spearheaded the design and development of a payroll and HR application based on <u>Agile Development Process</u>, leveraging the concepts of <u>Object Oriented Design</u> including Use case models, UML, Design patterns etc.
- Our application facilitated the easy management of human resources, payroll calculation and payslip generation for small to medium scale enterprises.

Asynchronous Canvas Sharing

Apr 2016

- Implemented a web based tool where multiple users could share a drawing board and make changes in real-time. It included a text chat with predictive texting.
- We extensively used <u>SVG</u>, <u>iQuery</u> and <u>MYSQL</u> to develop this application modeled on Client-Server architecture.

www.1000smiles.in

Mar 2014

- Designed the website and used <u>SEO</u> techniques to improve its visibility.
- 1000Smiles is an NGO based in India that focuses primarily on the welfare of underprivileged children.

ACHIEVEMENTS AND AWARDS

• Test Tool Development Competition (2nd prize), University of Texas at Dallas

Apr 2017

Graduate Scholarship, University of Texas at Dallas

Aug 2016

• Oracle Certificate of Excellence, Oracle Corporation

Feb 2016

- Co—authored a technical paper on implementing a low cost virtual supercomputing facility in a campus, which won numerous accolades.

 Sept 2011
- Top 0.5%ile All India Engineering Entrance (AIEEE) examination.

May 2008

• Top 0.3%ile - All India Pre-Medical Test (AIPMT) examination.

May 2008

LEADERSHIP EXPERIENCE AND ORGANIZATIONS

Volunteer and Co-Founder, 1000Smiles.in (NGO), India

Dec 2013-Jul 2016